Guide to the George A. Plimpton Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series IV: Organizations, 1889-1936
  - "Near East Relations"
    - Constantinople Women's College
      - Medical Education and the American Hospital, 1905- 1931, (2 folders) (Box 37, Folder 9 to 10)
      - School of Education, 1924-1927 (Box 38, Folder 1)
      - Visit, 1924 (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1930-1936 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Lausanne Treaty, 1925-1927 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Near East College Association, Inc., 1912- 1936 (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Relief
      - General, 1916- 1936 (Box 38, Folder 6)
      - Committee Reports, 1926-1927, (3 folders) (Box 38, Folder 7 to 9)
      - Committee Reports, 1927, (2 folders) (Box 39, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Trustees' Annual Report, 1928 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Peace
    - General, 1906- 1935, (3 folders) (Box 39, Folder 4 to 6)
    - Church Peace Union, 1914-1935 (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - Mexico--Relations and Scholarship Program, 1923- 1926 (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - World Peace Foundation, 1911-1925, 1935- 1936, (2 folders) (Box 40, Folder 3 to 4)
  - The Phillips Exeter Academy, 1902-1936, (2 folders) (Box 40, Folder 5 to 6)
  - Union Theological Seminary, 1912-1936, (5 folders) (Box 40, Folder 7 to 11)
- Series V: Writings and Lectures, circa 1850- 1947
  This series comprises notes, correspondence, and drafts relating to Plimpton's writings and lectures. Because subheadings and folder names were arranged alphabetically both in the previous "Subject File" and in the current arrangement, many folders retain their original order. Yet the introduction of several new subheadings has reordered several folders, and the discovery of loose notes and drafts required the creation of several new folders. The series includes Plimpton's correspondence and clippings regarding books that he either authored or supported, notes and drafts both of those writings and others, as well as lecture manuscripts and announcements.
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1909- 1947 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Commonwealth History of Massachusetts, 1927- 1928 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - The Education of Chaucer, 1934-1936, (2 folders) (Box 41, Folder 3 to 4)
    - The Education of Shakespeare, 1930- 1935 (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - The History of Elementary Mathematics in the Plimpton Library, 1910-1931 (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - Book: Rara Arithmetica, 1908-1922 (Box 41, Folder 7)
  - Lectures
    - Announcements, Invitations, and Clippings, 1929-1939 (Box 41, Folder 8)
    - Clippings, 1909- 1935 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Plimpton's Books, 1902- 1936 (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Manuscripts of Lectures, 1925-1926, 1931 (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - "A Talk on Education Before the Invention of Printing," undated (Box 42, Folder 4)
    - UCLA--"The Evolution of the Schoolbook"--Poster, 1927 (Box 52, Folder 25)
  - Notes and Drafts
    - Autobiography and Family History, undated (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - Education, undated (Box 42, Folder 6)
    - Education of Chaucer, Dante, and Shakespeare, undated (Box 42, Folder 7)
    - Education of Women, undated (Box 42, Folder 8)
    - "Farming in the South," undated (Box 42, Folder 9)
    - Notebook--History of Political Science, 1875 (Box 42, Folder 10)
    - "A Remarkable Exhibit of Scientific Manuscripts from the Library of George A. Plimpton," undated (Box 42, Folder 11)
    - Slavery Diary, undated (Box 42, Folder 12)
    - Smith, David Eugene, undated (Box 42, Folder 13)
  - Pamphlets and Printed Material--Colonial History
    - French and Indian War, 1877-1901 (Box 43, Folder 1)
    - New England Indians, [1850]-1896 (Box 43, Folder 2)
- Series VI: Collecting, 1693-1956
  This series includes not only extensive correspondence related to Plimpton's collecting of rare books, manuscripts, and artifacts but also examples of the items he collected. The majority of the general correspondence retains the original folder names and general arrangement.
  The remainder of the series contains several caches of material described only summarily by previous staff. One cache centers on penmanship and orthography, including handwriting samples, handwriting exercises, and an account book and general correspondence related to Alfred Manson, a Boston-based publisher of books on writing. Another cache of materials, dating from 1650-1869, centers on the American slave trade, including correspondence, documents, broadsides, pamphlets, and a slaveholder's account book.
  The series also includes a cache of documents related to Plimpton's collection of Western medieval manuscripts. These documents include Samuel A. Ive's detailed notes on many of the manuscripts in Plimpton's collection as well as correspondence and proof sheets related to De Ricci and Wilson's Census of Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts in the United States and Canada (1935-1937).
  - General
    - Bookplates, undated (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - Collection Descriptions and Notes, undated, (2 folders) (Box 44, Folder 2 to 3)
    - Correspondence--Carpentier, Horace Walpole, 1902- 1936 (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1898-1935, (5 folders) (Box 44, Folder 5 to 9)
    - Correspondence, 1935-1936, (3 folders) (Box 45, Folder 1 to 3)
  - Dealers--Correspondence
    - A-N, 1901- 1934, (7 folders) (Box 45, Folder 4 to 10)
    - Maggs Brothers--London, 1910-1934 (Box 46, Folder 1)
    - Medieval Manuscripts, 1905-1934 (Box 46, Folder 2)
    - O-Q, 1904-1934, (2 Folders) (Box 46, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Quaritch, Bernard, 1901-1933 (Box 46, Folder 5)
    - R-S, 1910-1932 (Box 46, Folder 6)
    - Ricketts, C. Lindsay, 1911-1936 (Box 46, Folder 7)
    - Rosenthal, 1902-1933 (Box 46, Folder 8)
    - T-V, 1906-1934 (Box 46, Folder 9)
    - Voynich, Wilfred M., 1902-1930 (Box 46, Folder 10)
    - W, 1902-1930 (Box 46, Folder 11)
  - Exhibits, 1911-1936 (Box 46, Folder 12)
  - Exhibits, 1911-1936 (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - Plimpton Library
    - General, 1917-1938 (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1910-1923 (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Requests to Visit and Talks, 1908- 1936 (Box 47, Folder 4)
- Portraits, 1901-1956, (2 folders) (Box 47, Folder 5 to 6)
- Portraits--Catalogues, 1905-1936 (Box 47, Folder 7)
- Scrapbook--Mathematical Specimens, 1903 (Box 48, Folder 1)
- Wellesley College, 1892- 1935 (Box 48, Folder 2)
- Penmanship, Calligraphy, and Orthography
  - American Manuscript Specimens of Handwriting, [1860]-1875 (Box 49)
  - Alfred Manson
    - Account Book--Penmanship Samples, undated, 1873 (Box 50)
    - Forms Sent to Manson, 1887 -1888 (Box 48, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, 1872-1903 (Box 48, Folder 4)
    - National System of Penmanship --Working Copy--Payson, Dunton & Scribner, 1879-1881 (Box 48, Folder 5)
    - Scribner, W. M., 1887- 1888 (Box 48, Folder 6)
    - Tracings, undated (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Oversize, 1800- 1978 (Mapcase 14-H-06)
  - Oversize, Undated (Mapcase 14-H-06)
- Slavery
  - Voyage of Judith Snow and Transcriptions, undated, 1906 (Box 51, Folder 2)
  - Account Book--Oak Lawn Plantation, 1851- 1856 (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - Accounts--Slave Trading Ships, 1693- 1773 (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - Burritt, Elihu, undated, 1843, 1854 (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - "Committee for the Address of Women of Great Britain and Ireland on Slavery in the United States," 1751-1776, 1852 (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - Egyptian Papyrus--Photograph, 1930 (Box 52, Folder 5)
  - Lithograph--Cotton Plantation, undated (Box 52, Folder 6)
  - Ordinance of Secession of the State of Alabama, 1861, (facsimile) (Box 52, Folder 7)
  - Printed Material
    - Anti-Slavery, undated, 1860-1863 (Box 52, Folder 8)
    - Broadsides, 1728, 1769- 1773 (Box 52, Folder 9)
    - Pamphlets, 1789-1925 (Box 52, Folder 10)
  - General Documents
    - 1678- 1697 (Box 52, Folder 11)
    - 1728-1759 (Box 52, Folder 12)
    - 1760-1769 (Box 52, Folder 13)
    - 1770-1779 (Box 52, Folder 14)
    - 1780-1789 (Box 52, Folder 15)
    - 1790-1799 (Box 52, Folder 16)
    - 1800-1809 (Box 52, Folderr 17)
    - 1810-1821 (Box 52, Folder 18)
    - 1819-1829 (Box 52, Folder 19)
    - 1830-1839 (Box 52, Folder 20)
    - 1840-1849 (Box 52, Folder 21)
    - 1850-1859 (Box 52, Folder 22)
    - 1860-1869 (Box 52, Folder 23)
    - Undated (Box 52, Folder 24)
    - Oversize, Undated (Mapcase 14-H-07)
    - Oversize--Broadside, 1950 (Mapcase 14-H-07)
- Western Medieval Manuscripts
  - Census of Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts in the United States and Canada, De Ricci and Wilson's, 1935-1937 (Box 51)
    - Notes, undated, 1948 (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Proof Sheets--Plimpton Library, undated (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - Revision Instructions, 1949, (2 folders) (Box 51, Folder 5 to 6)
  - Samuel A. Ives' Notes
    - Ms. 58--Includes Transcription, undated, (2 folders) (Box 51, Folder 7 to 8)
    - Ms. 2, 3, 17, 43, 47, 52, 58, 60, 63, 95, 98, 100, 101, 116, 119 (Box 53)
- Series VII: Collecting--Catalogued, 1634- 1920
  This small series contains a collection of Presidential Autographs and of material related to other historical figures. It is arranged alphabetically.
  - Autographs of Presidents
    - Buchanan, James, 1830, 1867 (Box 56, Folder 1)
    - Fillmore, Millard, 1850 (Box 56, Folder 2)
    - Garfield, James, 1871 (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - Grant, Ulysses, 1865, 1867, (2 folders) (Box 56, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Hayes, Rutherford B., 1869 (Box 56, Folder 6)
    - Jackson, Andrew, 1826 (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - Jefferson, Thomas, 1805 (Box 56, Folder 8)
    - Johnson, Andrew, 1862 (Box 56, Folder 9)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, 1824, 1864, (2 folders) (Box 56, Folder 10 to 11)
    - McKinley, William, 1895 (Box 56, Folder 12)
    - Monroe, James, 1812 (Box 56, Folder 13)
    - Pierce, Franklin, 1854 (Box 56, Folder 14)
    - Polk, James, 1848 (Box 56, Folder 15)
    - Tyler, John, 1834 (Box 56, Folder 16)
    - Washington, George, 1769 (Box 56, Folder 17)
  - Historical Figures
    - Index of Historical Figures, undated (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - Arnold-Dewey, 1634-1920 (Box 57, Folder 2)
    - Dodsley-Haslewood, 1664-1903 (Box 57, Folder 3)
    - Henry-Pike, 1740-1910 (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - Ray-Wordsworth, 1732-1903 (Box 57, Folder 5)
    - General, 1869 (Box 57, Folder 6)
    - General--Russell Hastings--Autobiography and Genealogy, 1900 (Box 57, Folder 7)
    - General--Mary Jackson--Autograph Album of Verses, 1830- 1838 (Box 57, Folder 8)